can we design in a sustainable faire
anti fragile future that liberates our
descendants they live meaningful lives
absolutely not however what we can do is
navigate to such a world and this at
first may seem like a very minor
difference but I think actually the
difference is major and when people come
to understand it it will I hope
free us from certain facile notions that
we often pick up and point us in the
direction of useful replacements that's
what I mean by that
those of us who make objects think of
something and then try to bring it into
the world whether it's a piece of
furniture or a machine of some kind get
familiar with the process of prototyping
a prototype is on the one hand a little
bit paradoxical if you view it in
isolation so if you if you make a
prototype of some machine that you think
would be useful to have that prototype
is liable to be clumsy it's liable not
to be intuitive it's liable to be
inefficient and so the amount of time
and effort that you put into building a
prototype tends to far outstrip whatever
savings or improvement you would get out
of the thing but that's not really the
product of a prototype a prototype is
not designed to solve the problem that
it is built around it is designed to
teach you what you don't know so that
you can make an object that ultimately
will save time and energy or make you
more effective at doing something so
what we need to understand is that very
often the inventor does not realize
enough of a savings or an improvement to
justify the massive expenditure in a
series of prototypes the market pays
them to do this work by getting a bunch
of people to buy the end product so each
of the prototypes may be very expensive
in terms of time and resources but the
end product is then something that you
can produce many copies of and people
will will get to use them if we
understood that when we are attempting
to structure a society that we are
actually involved in the same process
that we should know where in our minds
have the idea that we know so much about
the way human beings function or the way
systems are going to interact with human
psychology that we can design a system
that works really really well but
instead what we can do is separate the
problem into puzzles that we can solve
and build a prototype that tells us if
we're in the right neighborhood and then
teaches us what we don't
now about the interactions of certain
mechanisms for example then we can get
there so what I've been saying for the
last several years is that it is
relatively easy actually surprisingly
easy to figure out what values we should
share and therefore what a successful
civilization would have to do in order
for us to regard it as as such once we
name those values and we figure out some
prioritization mechanism so that we can
figure out when their attention between
these things if they're always are in
which way that tension should pull we
can begin to prototype a mechanism that
that returns on those those values it is
a navigation problem more than it is a
design problem you do have to design a
prototype but that prototype will reveal
the opportunities that you've bypassed
it will reveal flaws and your thinking
and it will allow you to take the next
step and so I would argue that this is
almost that navigation is almost literal
but we obviously use navigation as a
metaphor but that when we think of an
engineer as designing a mechanism they
are basically bringing a physical
hypothesis into being that hypothesis
tests their understanding of how other
systems interact and then they bring a
next version into being and it is a it
is like traversing design space in an
effort to achieve some objective in
building a better civilization that is
what we must do and you know the
founders founding fathers of the United
States knew this to some extent they
understood that they were not building a
final product they understood that there
were things about the future that they
couldn't anticipate and they expected us
to modify their
a great deal I have course can't know
but I suspect they would be shocked at
how reluctant we've been to modify their
experiment we have to be a bit more
proactive though the founders did not
know about adaptive evolution they
didn't understand that they were
building a system that would evolve over
time and because they didn't understand
that they didn't build in the proper
safeguards to deal with the fact that an
evolutionary system doesn't necessarily
do what you spell out in setting and in
motion it does whatever the niches that
it finds dictate that it should do we
have to anticipate that and to realize
that many of the niches that the system
we build we'll find are things that we
don't want it to discover or exploit we
do not want it for example taking
advantage of defects in our social
architecture it does not we do not want
our governmental structure for example
to facilitate human beings and gaming
other human beings that's something that
we would like to stamp out and we would
like it to allow people to explore
mechanisms that actually enhance the
lives of other people so we have to
recognize that that's not a natural
phenomenon that nature involves
creatures exploiting other creatures all
the time if we allow markets to simply
explore space they will discover many
things that are valuable and desirable
but they will discover maybe even more
things that are net negative for the
population there's no reason to allow
markets to dictate what it is that we
can do just simply on the basis of
whatever is profitable we have to guide
them we have to effectively take the
awesome power that is contained in
markets and harness it so that it
produces
things that are honorable and good and
doesn't produce things that are
parasitic or destructive
so we've got a navigation problem on our
hands naming the values that the system
should pursue is not so difficult most
people would agree that we want a system
that is safe sustainable fair and that
effectively liberates people to choose
how to live that those would be
desirable things people will differ over
what priority to give these different
values we have to figure out how to
navigate that fairly so if most people
in society prefer a bit more safety we
have to make allowances for that in
other words we don't want those people
who prioritize freedom over all other
things to put us all in jeopardy because
they have a particular relationship with
risk but we have to figure out how these
things are prioritized how to change
those priorities over time as the
population changes what it desires and
then we have to navigate to a system
that stabili generates these things
human beings are a product of adaptive
evolution we are adapted to the
circumstances that our ancestors faced
on the way to the present those
adaptations many of them are useful
still and some of them are actually an
existential threat to our continued
survival for example we are evolved for
population against population
competition and that population against
population competition is an existential
threat in an era where some populations
have large nuclear arsenals where
biological warfare is going to become
increasingly accessible at a
technological level to smaller and
smaller powers
we can't allow a world that is governed
by small tyrannical forces that wish to
deploy technology against the average
citizen
so we have to somehow negate that risk
that risk comes from our built-in
competition between populations our
tendency to compete with other
populations and to cooperate therefore
with our own population has been a key
to the success of all the populations
that exist currently on the earth today
and it is now an existential threat
going forward so somehow we have to
neutralize the tendency of that instinct
to control our behavior and that is
going to require us to make sure that
the experience that people have that the
world that they see does not trigger
their xenophobia that it triggers their
collaborative instincts and this is
actually a process that has been
evolutionarily unfolding for thousands
of years where what once would have been
a feeling of affinity for a tiny number
of individuals all of whose names you
knew is now a feeling of affinity for a
large population mostly anonymous to you
so the selection has been engineering a
sense of shared purpose over larger and
larger populations and we have to take
the final step where that a sense of
shared fate actually extends to all
people so the future is an awesome
well our future is not headed in the
direction of awesome at the moment which
I realize is out of phase with the
conventional wisdom of the moment that
these are the best of times and things
are less violent and more prosperous
than they've ever been in which there's
a certain amount of truth in that but
the problem is if we separate out the
various values that we might pursue
we're doing really well on some and
really terribly on others and
unfortunately the places that we are
doing worst have to do with the
sustainability of our mechanisms of
living
and the fragility that we have invited
into our system so although things are
comparatively easy if you are decently
positioned in society comparatively good
relative to where an ancestor might have
been 100 or 200 years ago but they are
not fair
that is to say depending upon what
population you're born into your access
to opportunity will vary tremendously so
that is something that needs to be
corrected and it is also the case that
even if things could be made fair that
we are essentially gambling with the
hazards that we face the
interconnectedness of civilization and
the exponential technology that we
utilize are putting us in grave danger
over the long term and I think this is
one of them this most serious problems
is that because our day-to-day existence
is relatively easy I mean even if you
have a a rotten job in civilization the
number of hazards that have been taken
care of on a day to day level is most of
them
they're more people for example who are
obese than starving these days so the
greatest hazard that ancestors would
have faced has apparently been taken out
of first place starvation is not an
issue at the moment but what that means
is that somatically we're getting the
wrong messages about how secure we are
that our day-to-day lives aren't that
difficult but our long-term prospects
are actually not so hot so effectively
we have to address this puzzle we have
to make civilization sustainable and I
would argue that if you made it
sustainable but you didn't make it fair
it wouldn't stick so essentially we're
faced with the puzzle of either finally
addressing all of these puzzles together
or building something that might reduce
jeopardy of one kind or another but
would only last temporarily so how can
you convince people that it's not
sustainable
because people are kind of programmed to
think about how good they have it I
think this may be the greatest challenge
that we've got is that as long as people
are well-fed they don't tend to believe
even robust mathematical analyses that
tell us very well that we are burning up
resources that are not renewable and I
must say I think
one reason for hope is that we actually
may be closing in on viable fusion power
infusion unlike fusion power fusion
power could potentially plug into all of
our systems and allow us lots of leeway
to do remarkable things including
reverse global warming if we can scale
it up it sucked the heat out of the air
not suck the heat out but suck the
carbon out of the atmosphere so fusion
power offers a great deal of hope but if
we deploy it without figuring out the
other puzzles then we run the danger of
just amplifying and Justices in the
system that will ultimately destabilize
us or it will cause a massive burst in
consumption that will cause one
generation to feel suddenly very
well-off but its descendants will be
faced with an even more precipitous
problem how should we ascertain fairness
and because we've both seen how fairness
can be used abusively yeah so how do we
accurately gauge that well this is one
of these places where there is room for
reasonable people to disagree over let's
say how unequal outcomes can be and
still be tolerated but I don't think
there's any room for reasonable people
to disagree both
the distribution of opportunity that all
of us if we are honest brokers who are
interested in the well-being of the
entire population should be interested
in seeing opportunity as broadly
distributed as possible and we can
easily detect that opportunity is not
evenly distributed because schools
different quality because zip codes
differ in the degree to which they
prepare you for adult life so once we
get close to fairness it will be a lot
harder to answer that question but I
think we have far enough to go that it's
it's not so difficult isn't like
arriving at fairness in a sense a
redistribution of advantage not
necessarily wealth but advantage like
there will be losers because there are
winners now in the system or can you
convince people that everybody's gonna
be a winner
well that's why I like this formulation
the fact is I believe that an adult
perspective has to recognize that you
will have differences in outcome based
on how dedicated individuals are some
people may prefer to go spend time on
the beach and be willing to live in a
smaller house to do so and I frankly
couldn't tell them that they were wrong
to make that choice that's a valid set
of priorities on the other hand
opportunity has been hoarded by certain
populations and it does so for a reason
which is to say it is rational to keep
other children from having the
advantages that your children have that
provides your children a head start in
life over their competitors so I can
understand the desire to do that it's
rational it's immoral but it's rational
what I cannot abide is anybody who
argues that it is defensible to deny
some people opportunity and then hold
them responsible for the outcomes in
their lives either we all have equal
opportunity and then we can be held
accountable for the outcomes in our
lives where we don't have equal
opportunity in which case we have a
responsibility to people who were denied
opportunity to take care of them seems
to me that you end up in one of those
two places inevitably and I would far
prefer to see people liberated to
produce great stuff to see them
empowered to do it and then if some
people want to take it as leisure time
and other people want to dedicate
themselves to the project and they want
to they're willing to endure the
consequence of living in very different
circumstances that's fine by me well but
then their children
Goldin suffer their choices and then
there will eventually be unfairness
again in the system there can be but
what I don't want to see is a you know
yes if your parents decided to recover
the fraction of Civilizations surplus
that they were due and they want to take
it as leisure and you're the child of
somebody who is prioritized leisure and
you prioritize accomplishment it can't
be so far out of range that you can't
get there from the house you were born
into so I do think civilization has an
obligation to make opportunity available
to those who wish to use it kind of like
an open-ended opportunity
like every generation every new life is
given a fair shake that seems
preposterous at one level but when you
think about the vast fortunes that we
spend on frivolous stuff it doesn't seem
so far out of range but we spend a
hundred and twenty billion dollars a
year on text messages a hundred and
twenty billion dollars a year on text
messages they're only like it's about
hundred forty characters in fact they're
free to the telecoms because they are
transmitted on the signal that your
phone uses to keep in touch with the
tower
they're not even transmitted over the
main bandwidth but we we charge you
something like fifteen hundred dollars
per megabyte to send text messages where
those same that same megabyte would cost
a sense if you send it over email it
makes no sense to us at all but the
point is because it's a small part of
our bill we don't even notice that huge
expenditure so my point would be
if you took things that are really not
essential and really not useful and
productive and you repurposed a small
amount of the resource that we dedicate
to those things to human well-being an
opportunity so that a child was born
into you know even a child is born into
a defective family they deserve for the
structures that they encounter in school
to provide them the opportunity to say
hey you know what family I came from
doesn't speak for me I want to do
something different why would we ever
deny a child the ability to rise above
their parents compromised values if
that's what they want to do taking that
text message example like and following
it a little bit somebody in a company
was paid money to increase the value of
that company for the shareholders so
they expended their time and energy to
game this little tiny system and then
generate this huge amount of profit how
do you incentivize people whose job it
is to maximize shareholders - and the
whole system is rigged so that the
shareholders are expected to get more
return on their investment how do you
how do you fix that whole system with
the text messaging example that
generated this huge amount of wealth
that doesn't even matter to anything it
just it's more money and how do you do
tax that these people whose job it is to
create more wealth is that where you
text
well this is where I say it is a mistake
to descend into the policy layer
prematurely my point would be our whole
system is broken and if you want to
solve the expenditure on text messages
all a cart then people will scream
bloody murder that you're interfering
with their opportunity rather than
somebody else's opportunity why are you
going after text messages rather than
the porn industry yeah right and in fact
it's an impossible puzzle to solve but
the point I want to make it's not about
text messages being the source of
revenue to solve the problem of failing
schools my point is do you realize how
many activities that are almost totally
frivolous we invest you
huge sums of money in and my point is
not that some particular thing is the
place to recover that revenue my point
is we have a system that generates
absolutely immense abundance and then
wastes it and my point would be you
could take some of that abundance and
you could turn it into opportunity for
people who are trapped in a system
that's going to keep them perpetually
hobbled and then hold them responsible
for hey did you make use of the
opportunity or didn't you if you had a
good opportunity and you squandered it I
think we can afford to be less
sympathetic but if you didn't have the
opportunity not being sympathetic it's
just simply inhumane well you were
talking about earlier as suspending the
policy argument and getting took some
sort of foundational understanding so
that we can start to understand the
tools that we need to solve these
problems on a conceptual level or a
narrative level that would include some
sort of understanding of some sort of
ethical understanding of human being
some sort of sympathy synthetic
understanding of other people we
unfortunately because of the situation
that our ancestors found themselves in
our overly focused on us as individuals
the experience of being an individual is
very compelling right it's
neurologically compelling but it's
actually an accident it's an accident of
the fact that your ancestors didn't have
the ability to affect things far from
them or distant into the future and so
you are focused on those things not that
are important but those things about
which you have the potential to make
useful interventions and so human beings
are focused on their individuality we
should be focused on the fact that we
are hurtling around the Sun on a small
rock in which we are interconnected in
ways that make us fragile and could deny
potential future human beings from ever
getting experienced to live here on
earth and
to enjoy the fruits of our ancestors
labor that's stupid we really you know
it sounds trite but if you can just tune
in just for a moment to the idea that
what unites us actually far exceeds what
divides us and that we live in an era
where our technological sophistication
makes us capable of producing a surplus
that could effectively free every person
to live well and do useful stuff we need
education to understand how powerful we
are and that means that we can affect
the future and the space that we share
much greater than our ancestors could
absent and so we need to upgrade our
understanding which would include like
just a broadening of our awareness of
how powerful we are we need to upgrade
our software and the fact is upgrading
our software is something humans have
done again and again and you know you
can look at religious texts and you can
see them as upgrades sequential upgrades
that increase what people are capable of
properly navigating and what we need
essentially is the first upgrade that is
aware of what it is that it is aware
that what it is doing is changing our
understanding of our own place in
history and our responsibility to each
other and in particular a responsibility
to future inhabitants of the planet that
we are both in a greater position to
damage their birthright and in a greater
position to understand in what way we
might protect it and that that carries
responsibilities which is the downside
but again the hardest part to compel
people up but the one that I think is
most important is were we to take that
project seriously we're we to look
around the planet and say actually you
know what I'm wired to be suspicious of
people from other populations but once I
get over that and once I see history for
what it is and I see my own role for
what it is that actually the project
that we've been handed that the living
generations have been handed the
greatest project of all time the most
route
warding the most heroic exactly it is
heroic imagine for a second that you
happen to be alive at the moment that
humanity is going to rise to some kind
of collective consciousness and take
responsibility for making the future
really really good right now if a
utopian said that you should be very
frightened all right a utopian who
speaks that way is in danger of
architecting something very dangerous
this is why I'm saying it's really
important to stay away from utopian
ideas at all costs I'm not telling you I
know how to take ownership of our
responsibility for the future but I do
know in what direction it is right that
that responsibility is the result of a
process of discovery so what I get from
you about utopia and why find it
problematic is that it imagines an end
which is static and you want to put the
focus on the process the the end isn't
the goal it the process is the go you're
looking for a healthy process which I
guess would be more evolutionary you see
something as a dynamic that that will
constantly need to be adjusted it will
need to be adjusted
it must be enlightened what do you mean
by it
it must be aware of what it is that is
being maintained and what it is that is
being maintained is not so difficult you
know the fact is if you think about a
jetliner from the perspective of the
Wright brothers the idea that you would
have this pressurized capsule that flies
high enough so that the air is so thin
that exposed to it for even a minute
you'd black out but that we can maintain
the pressure we can maintain the
temperature we can maintain an
orientation in the jet stream enough
that the pilot will know where the plane
is and can put it down with precision
reliably enough that hundreds of people
will step off and collect their baggage
and go on about their business that's
hard to imagine from the perspective of
the Wright brothers given what they were
dealing with in their
prototype yeah on the other hand it's
all doable right you the airplane isn't
infinitely complex it is complex enough
to maintain the various feedback so that
you never get on an airplane and you
know have the temperature dropped 20
degrees doesn't happen if the Wright
brothers had with their current
understanding of technology or what they
were trying to do locked their entire
project and all future aircraft into
this one conception that they had right
there that would be kind of utopianism
like we're gonna do this and damn
reality this is what's gonna work but
instead they're like okay what what we
need to do right now is get this thing
off the ground that's all we're going to
concentrate on just getting this thing
off the ground and sending it a mile
bingo okay bingo and I mean think about
I mean it's the perfect example right
1903 the Wright brothers finally get
enough stuff right to get off the ground
long enough to say heavier-than-air
flight has been accomplished in 1903
1969 we land human beings on the moon
they play golf and fly home okay that's
a pretty short run from getting off the
ground for 30 seconds to landing on the
moon and playing golf yeah right it's a
pretty short period of time and all that
stuff and everything that that was and
everything that was generated from that
was an inconceivable to the Wright
brothers all that aluminum all that fuel
all all the different subsidiary yep
technological advancements required just
to get this thing to keep on going
forward they couldn't have seen it
coming on the other hand if you look at
what they could see coming
the Wright brothers were able to do an
amazing amount between 1903 when they
got off the ground for the first time in
1909 for example all of the people who
were trying to
discover how to make heavier-than-air
flight had the same set of problems to
solve and really it was a set of things
you needed an engine powerful enough you
needed the engine to be light enough you
know all of the powerful engines were
heavy because it wasn't so hard if you
had wheels under them to deal with the
weight of them so they needed to get the
engine light they need to get it
efficient they needed to get the control
of the aircraft good enough that it
didn't squander energy in turning and
staying stable and they needed the
airfoils to be aerodynamically efficient
all of those things had to be right in
order to get off the ground the first
time once they got off the ground the
first time they knew more they were the
world's leading experts in aviation and
so having gotten off the ground the
first time it was clear what direction
to head getting off the ground the first
time required intuition about how to
solve all of those little puzzles they
had to make an engine that was light
enough they had to get into fishing they
had to get the control of the airplane
down which they didn't have right at
first they used this wing warping thing
was pretty inefficient but the wind
tunnel was designed so that they could
see the cross-sections of wing that were
most effective in the wind and they were
in some sense I think it was luck I
don't know that they knew that this
would be the case some things don't
scale there are lots of things that if
you make a small version that works and
then you just scale it up it'll fall
apart bingo
yes communism well there's a famous
aviation example of this actually
Langley's aerodrome so Langley is like a
battle like
like a WWF battler see well Langley was
a military guy and he was trying to win
the competition to make heavier-than-air
flight first and he had a toy called the
arrow drum that flew heavier than air
flight but it didn't carry a person and
so anyway he scaled this toy up to
immense size and he invited the press so
there's actually film of this and he
launched it off this barge an elevated
barge nothing launched off the barge and
literally crumbled into the sea right
it's a very dramatic failure and the
only thing that was wrong was that he
didn't realize that he had a non
scalable design that he would have had
to modify it substantially so anyway the
Wright brothers were correct that you
could check an airfoil at small size and
discover how it would function in the
wind at large size yeah they also
prototyped a lot of stuff at full size
right so all of the practice that they
did over several summers at Kitty Hawk
involved full-size prototypes that they
flew in the wind sometimes they flew
them as kites then they flew them as
gliders then ultimately they flew them
as an airplane so they were doing work
at full scale and they were doing work
in miniature and the two things combined
and beautifully the thing is about a
society though that it's so complex that
there's not going to be any person
that's going to understand even one
whole of like the project that they're
working on like health care or any other
Gooden thing how do you develop in a
society trust across all these different
expertise assists expertise ease it
involves alignment and part of the
problem that we face is that we are not
we are not yet enough aligned to trust
each other but
there are I think we would have to
borrow from ancient wisdom in terms of
how to align ourselves but frankly what
I've seen in the last nine months
suggests that
there is a hunger for people who are
authentic to
to attempt this job and what surprised
me most is that many people who are
quite aware that they don't agree with
me politically are still listening
because at some level I think they
detect that
I mean really patriotism is the the core
parameter that there's a big difference
between listening to somebody who you
disagree with but who you believe is
fundamentally rather ready to sacrifice
for the same cause and therefore you
know that their disagreement is actually
motivated not by a self-interest or
something but by a difference in their
understanding of how to achieve some
shared goal if we can get to that page
where we can say hey we all agree in the
experiment we all agree that the
objectives are these and we disagree
over what will lead us to those
objectives and then we can have a
rational conversation if you suspect
that people are actually advocating for
their own interests while pretending to
be trying to solve a societal puzzle
then you tend to you know lock down
whatever you have control over so that
it can't be accessed by those people you
don't trust
so anyway we do have to keep people who
are not trustworthy away from power
there needs to be some sort of wind
tunnel for authenticity but that's a
great point yeah a wind tunnel for
authenticity that'd be cool yeah now we
can make a wind tunnel to test for
toupees but I don't know that that
that's probably not the same